[Music]
hello and welcome our customers tell us
that they want more data more
productivity with less keystrokes and
less mouse Clicks in this session we're
going to show you some of the highlights
from business Central's 2023 release
Wave 2 where we've improved the web
client in terms of these kind of
productivity features and it's mostly
based on your feedback uh my name is
Mike borj Cardon I'm a product manager
at Microsoft and today I'm joined by my
colleague Ivan also a product manager at
Microsoft and in this session we'll
cover how to get to your data more
quickly uh we'll look at new ways to
really dig into the details of your data
um whether you're performing quick
analytical tasks or maybe
troubleshooting some kind of
configuration error and we'll sneak in a
few good to know tips as well along the
way in relation to the web
client so let's dive into our first
topic which is navigation um our users
spend a good part of their day uh going
from page a to page B from record one to
record two navigating around business
Central to get their tasks done uh so we
really want to help them get around more
quickly and more reliably so to help me
tell the story here is Ian so thanks
Mike I'm so excited to be part of this
session and to show you how to get to
your data faster when using business
Central every single one of our users
looks up related data be through a
simple or Advanced lookup some of them
simply simply pick values to enter While
others use them to get to record details
2023 release Wave 2 brings you 60 to 80%
productivity boost in these scenarios
depending on whether you prefer to use
mouse or keyboard when looking up
related data details you must be
wondering how well we've added show
details to all simple lookup dialogues
so that users that love using Mouse to
navigate to record details can utilize
that new keyboard shortcut was added
it's called it's uh Control Alt down and
it navigates the user to the related
data definition this keyboard shortcut
works on simple and advanced lookups
with records that have card Pages or not
you can think of it this way the alt
down that you currently use for lookup
will take you to a noneditable list and
the new Control Alt down will take you
directly to a card great news for our
partners is that there is no uptake of
this it's just there in your existing
and your new code in
2023 release Wave 2 well this is one of
the ways to get your data faster in 2022
to release Wave 2 uh let's see what else
is there
nothing beats search in terms of getting
to your data fast research shows that
users spend up to 20% of their working
time searching for information finding
specific information in a timely manner
across different areas of business
management solution often requires
tailored queries within its different
parts because of the volume of the data
constantly increases it's becoming
increasingly important to get to the
relevant content fast so business
Central allows you to search across
company data that's relevant for your
role and not just business transactions
and in 2023 release Wave 2 in a very
familiar way so simply press the
well-known alt Q to open tell me and
start searching for your company data
get into company data search through
tell me improves discoverability of this
capability and aligns business Central
with user experiences that you're used
to in other Microsoft and Dynamics 365
products when on editable page currently
focused Fields value is automatically
copied to tell me enabling you to search
across company data that's relevant for
your role and data that you have access
to optimized search result page also
allows you to focus on search results
while making sure search is performant
and can easily be tailored to your needs
and with this release tell me is also
available on business Central mobile app
but there's a separate session that goes
into more details on this
let's see these improvements in action
as slides and screenshots are just not
enough to show how powerful they are
we'll start in the sales orders list and
the thing that you might have noticed is
we have this sort of Peak View that
allows you to to get to to details of
record and it's pretty convenient even
if you're using keyboard you can simply
press enter and another enter it will
take you to the card right this is a
sort of a list and non-editable uh card
page uh experience as this works only
with a
non-editable pages but let's say that
you want to uh have a look at some data
uh while you are editing a sales order
the first thing that you will notice
when you open the lookup right there is
this new show details action which takes
you directly to the customer
card what you can also do as I've uh
explained previously you can press
control alt down and it just takes you
to the card right this was a simple
lookup if we move on to a u Advanced
lookup pressing Control Alt down does
exactly the same thing now you might be
wondering what about
these uh what about these pages that
actually don't have a card page one of
these is uh country or region code right
pressing control all down actually takes
you to the list and what you can see in
here is it also uh filters out the
record uh that was uh
selected let's move a bit further uh
below and let's see what happens with a
with a lookup where we don't have a uh
where we don't have a value selected you
see that the show details is now
disabled but another neat neat trick
that you can see in here if you if you
press alt down you can actually go and
pick a random record in here and
pressing Control Alt down will simply
take you to the car
uh even without selecting it that feels
so so
powerful another thing that I wanted to
show you was if I go to the customer
name and now press that wellknown altq
thing what you see is that that customer
name that was selected in here was
copied directly to the tell me all I
have to do is either click search
company data or press enter and the
company data search is actually
started and in here you can see all the
details that you might have uh said that
are of course relevant for your role
that have that to which you have
permissions for and so on plus uh the
users can actually go and customize
which data uh to
search another NE trick is uh you can
even select a text like this press alt Q
the selected text prop is there press
enter and again you get to the data
search and uh this new and improved uh
search results page is now actually very
smart you see in here we have found
something on the purchase order line and
clicking on that search result it's not
going to open the purchase order line
but it knows that that line lives in the
context of the purchase order and it
opens that particular
page so that's how we enhance tel me but
wait wait there's more there's a new
Link in tell me and navigation pain that
helps with reports can you tell us a bit
more about this mic that's right Evan so
those of you with sharp eyes may have
also noticed actually two new links here
one in tell me which says uh explore
reports and another one on the RO Center
homepage which also says all reports so
what is this all about well our
customers tell us that they struggle
sometimes to find business centrals
reports and other analytical
capabilities so those links now lead to
this experience um this screen that
gives an overview of all of the reports
that may be organized by Department uh
by role um this is really an adaptation
of what we call the role Explorer uh
here we're simply focusing in on reports
in particular now this is based on links
uh from your role Center homepages to
report objects and I'll show up all over
here and give you that big overview
where you can find and search those
reports many times um it's not it's not
about you personally getting around
business Central sometimes it's about
sharing data with others so they can get
to data quickly uh if you have ever
shared a link to a record uh over email
or maybe into a teams Channel or
possibly into one note as you see on
this screen here in this example here
I've pasted Three Links to three
different um item records right uh
you'll noce sometimes those links don't
look great they don't give it a lot of
context so in this wave business Central
uh web client introduces a very simple
and consisent naming scheme a naming
pattern um that really helps links show
up as a lot more readable and
understandable they give a bit more
context just enough context actually to
help you understand what's at the end of
that
link um and this works when pasting
links into uh any Rich Text Editor
inside any app but if you do paste the
link into a simple plain text field or
maybe inside something like uh apps like
like uh Windows notepad you'll still get
the raw URL displayed over
there now just to give you a sense of
why our customers gave us feedback on
this well previously links looked
something like this they contained too
little information in many cases look at
that edit item card well can you guess
which item record this actually links to
no right sometimes we were over
informative um too much information just
made the link hard to read um and if you
were sharing this with your co-workers
over email you'd find yourself trimming
the link down a little bit so it doesn't
look so silly uh so here um you know
there's for example a prefix which says
edit there is a suffix which has the
brand name and that's all unnecessary
when you're sharing this link with your
co-workers finally links were also
inconsistent so how you navigate it to
the record would ultimately determine
what the link looks like when you copy a
link to that record and paste it
elsewhere and here is what links look
like today they're clean they're more
readable they give just the right amount
of context even the names of your list
views or even the analysis tabs appear
in the link when you share it with
others it's one of those really small
things that uh just make a big
difference to your workday so go forth
and paced with
confidence now before we get to the next
section just want to take a minute to uh
share a few things related to the web
client that I think are really good for
you to know about a year ago we
announced that Legacy list views are
going away um we're deprecating Legacy
list views in update 23 is what we said
back then that's the older model inal of
you know creating a filtered list and
you'd have to bake that into your role
Center or you could create Legacy list
views through the UI in in the past um
but we'd like to give our community a
little bit more time to act and migrates
their legacy list views over to the
newer model so we have a new timeline
for this which is please do this by
update 24 so when update 24 4 which is
approximately April 2024 um Legacy list
views will go away they will disappear
from the web client so make sure you act
in good time similarly we're also
extending the time until we fully roll
out the change where the web client
automatically saves uh the field value
as you click or Tab out of a field uh
this change will automatically be
enabled for everyone also in update 24
and that is roughly April
2024 now here's another goodie for you
to know about uh We've improved the
business Central platform uh so that
developers can now Implement Rich
content Fields uh and do that natively
in Al code without having to use control
add-ins or build their own add-ins um
each reach Rich content field uh it
stretches to fill all of the horizontal
space on the screen um it is multi-line
uh but it has a maximum height and it
comes with a toolbar with over 25
different functions and their
corresponding keyboard short Cuts uh to
really help you do things like format
your text add new lines insert pictures
uh insert tables as well um and I'll
paste content in there as well for
example you could be pasting the same
hyperlinks I mentioned a moment ago so
we know this this session is mostly
watched by our customers or end users uh
or Consultants or salespeople so do use
this opportunity to talk to your
developers about this experience that
you can now bring into business Central
uh with your extensions and with your
customizations uh for example you may
want to use this if you are dealing with
uh product information management where
you need that rich description
multimedia content to be in this space
uh maybe you're dealing with Rich
annotation of your records or even just
using business Central to you know
author social media content as in this
example right
here so let's switch gears now and look
at how we're helping users really dig
into their data once they found it find
anomalies get them blocked faster and
for that I'd like to switch over again
to Ivan uh Ian what does this look like
in wave two thanks Mike to help you
resolve issues when working with
business Central in 2023 release Wave 1
in July update we've added actions to
aor message dialogues making aor message
dialogues more user friendly helps build
trust with business Central and saves
Time by making it easier to correct
issues users can quickly get to a
potential source of an error in business
Central and receive guidance to get to
resolution
faster the collectible errors and check
documents and journals while you work
capabilities help produce inter
interruptions and give you an overview
of posting errors while you work on the
journal or document actionable errors
help you fix typical errors when posting
Dimensions which can save time when you
are processing a large
document uh error message page includes
recommended actions to fix uh the error
and supports applying recommendations in
bulk across multiple errors using accept
recommended action
action uh in the first iteration we
provide users with capability to fix
Dimension code related errors when
Dimension posting rules require
Dimension to be the same or Dimension
code must be blank we've also improved
the user experience of error messages
page making most prominent information
easily accessible in the list of errors
and the the ones that are less prominent
in the details fact box on top of that
there's an interface for Al developers
to add their custom fixes for custom
errors to get to parity with actionable
error dialogues in 2023 release Wave 2
we've also improved inline validation
dialogues as they are also a surface
they also surface errors during data
entry users now get navigate and uh fix
it actions on validation errors
that either take you there to a problem
so you can fix it or have business
Central fix it for you when
possible uh clear and actionable error
information in validation messages helps
you quickly resolve errors or pass on
the details to your admin or support or
revert changes that cause the error
every inline validation dialogue now has
refresh and copy details actions inline
validation refresh action is now more
conveniently positioned closer to the
error itself itself and the copy details
actions now allows you to copy and share
four error details conveniently even
from the inline validation
error of course nothing bits seeing this
in action so let's dig into this in a
short demo so let's go back to our uh
sales
order and in here I will just go ahead
and try to change a quantity in here so
this is a sales order that uh um that
has an item that has that requires drop
shipment if you look at the if you look
at the error message you'll see that
improved error message in the inline uh
validation dialogue but you will also
see the action where we can the business
Central can now take you directly to
that purchase order that is linked to to
this uh sales order another thing that
you will notice in here is the
refresh uh or revert actions and the
copy details actions so clicking these
are more conveniently positioned right
now and uh clicking revert will revert
this and copy details will get you all
of that uh technical information that
you can pass on to uh to support and
share with your admin or a partner so
let's revert that one that this was an
example of U of an actionable error that
is just going to take you to another
place let's try to do another thing let
me try to change quantity to shipping
here right and you can see you get
another another type of error this is an
inline validation error that actually
allows you to fix the value because we
know what the expected value in here is
and we business Central can actually go
ahead and help you fix that issue what
you might have noticed also on the side
in here you have a document check check
box that collects the issues you
might have while you are working on this
document in this particular case I have
a
document that has has some Dimension
values uh that are not appropriate for
it that that do not comply to the rules
that were set in in the setup and in
here you can actually uh click on the
description to see the the full error
message you see that error messages now
have a title and a bit uh clear
explanation uh of the error what the
user can also do uh they can click on
the recommended action to go and simply
fix that particular
error
or another thing that you can do you can
actually go and and inspect you can see
that this error is coming from line
number two in that sales order that the
location of that error is in that Line's
Dimension set entry right we see in here
sales campaign is missing right so we in
order for us to to to correct this error
what the user would normally do would go
in here and add that uh sales campaign
uh entry and there's also a source of
source of the comes from the items
default Dimension setting where the
sales campaign requires summer to be set
for that particular item and of course
uh you can imagine the old way of doing
it it's going through each and every
line updating the dimensions and up
until you U it's like a lot of trial and
error what you can do also in here you
can just go ahead select the errors and
say I'll just want accept the
recommended action do this CL those and
in here you can see we've resolved all
the
errors I mean this this is really this
is really something very uh very
exciting and very something that can
boost your your productivity just you
know think about the old way of going
into this each line of the document or
journal and fixing things and the heated
discussions you might have had with your
controller about changes to Dimension
posting Ro in summary the demo showed
how business centrals action of errors
in standard and inline validation
dialogues help users unblock themselves
and help resolve problems faster next
Mike will show us how digging into Data
across companies and Pages Works in wave
two mike over to you in the studio when
business Central users multitask for
example pop out multiple windows so they
can compare information side by side or
use multiple tabs uh they always need to
know the context of what's inside that
window before switching to it for
example example with alt tab we've
applied the same simple and consistent
naming convention also to the title of
each Tab and that's very similar to what
I showed you earlier and this makes your
tabs a lot more readable understandable
at a glance uh especially if like me you
have a busy week and you end the week
with about 30 open tabs you need to know
what's in there
right tab names are now more clean
they're trimmed of unnecessary
information they just give the right
amount of context and uh which means you
now no longer need to alt Tab and
inspect what is inside each one of those
to figure out which tab you actually
looking for let's put this into practice
I'm going to show you a little demo of
this so let's imagine my task for today
is really digging into my data across
different companies I'm in the chart of
accounts list right now um I'm in the
cronis uh USA company I'd like to
compare some of that with what's in
another company kronis Chicago I'll use
the company switcher for this great
feature and and here I can actually
choose to open this same chart of
accounts in the other company in a new
tab with a click so here it is loading
up I've got uh chart of accounts for my
Chicago Company in a moment that will
appear on the screen now I may also want
to uh duplicate tabs let me just do that
and bring up in this one particular tab
here for the Chicago Company a
particular account and all the account
details and having these different tabs
here is really just going to help me
compare this information as I work
across uh these these companies let's
open up the Deferred tax
assets account there we go now I'm going
to use Microsoft Edge's feature here to
have uh vertical tabs so you can really
see the different tabs and what they are
named and what that looks like here I've
got chart of accounts for cronis that's
where I started I've got chart of
accounts for Chicago that's the company
I opened up and now I've got the GL
account for the F text assets for
Chicago so the tab names are super
useful now they really easy for me to
understand what's going to happen what
am I going to see when I click on each
of those and here if you set up the
company badge for each of these
companies the company badge will also
appear in the tab name to give you that
clue so this is really useful for our
users who use a lot of time in their day
switching across companies uh and
digging into that data and
comparing now um the naming for tabs
also feeds very interesting features in
your browser so for example here I'm
almost out of time with this task so I'd
like to continue from home on my home PC
so here's what I'm going to do I'm going
to say look let me select these tabs I'm
going to use a feature in Microsoft Edge
to start a new
collection there we go I now have a
collection up
here which includes my three tabs
there's a little thumbnail of what's in
the tab but also again those tab names
that are so indicative of what's in them
is also transferred into my collection
going to use another feature to add a
quick note
remember to review
Chicago and a great thing is this is all
saved and this particular uh collection
of links collection of tabs is now
something I can pick up where I left off
as soon as I get home from my home PC
Okay so we've seen now how the tab
naming is super easy super intuitive
nice and clean and gives you a lot of
context let's talk about another great
feature here uh We've enhanced a very
popular page inspection tool with a few
neat little changes that I really want
you to know about now page inspection is
a Swiss army knife of sorts uh it helps
you understand the underlying data model
uh for your your pages uh but also use
it to troubleshoot record data for
example that isn't shown on the page and
so much more so now clicking or
activating the field in the inspection
pane will actually scroll that field
into view on your page canvas making it
super easy for you to find these fields
that you're looking for let me give you
a really quick demo of this so you can
see how it works
let's start out on the vendor card here
I'm going to use the shortcut Control
Alt F1 that's going to slide in the page
inspection Pane and here I can see for
the current record which is the fabric
am vendor I can see all of the fields
and that's a lot of fields uh from this
table record let's start easy here I'm
just going to click on the number field
notice how instantly the number field on
the page has this visual indicator to
show me where it is fantastic let's make
this a little bit trickier I'm going to
search for I don't know
prepayment uh field it searches as it
types it finds one field that matches
from the table and that's the prepayment
percent field so Watch What Happens the
moment I click on
this the prepayment percent field now
has been scrolled into view on the page
and typically to find this field you
know this is actually quite buried
underneath the show more show less so
it's an additional field it's under the
payments fast tab so what is done has
created this really easy way for me to
get straight to that field so I can edit
it I can modify it I can copy it and so
on and so forth so if you're trying to
find fields on a rather big and complex
page page inspector has this handy
little feature now to really help you
get straight to those fields in no time
now that's what I call a really
efficient way to dig into your data on
the page and it works on any page but
there's also times where depending on
the issues that you're troubleshooting
with your data for example uh the more
techsavvy people really want to see well
what does this look like in code they
want to dig one level deeper well we've
got something for new for you as well
here uh you can now use this new Link in
the page inspection pane to explore this
page in Visual Studio code so for
example if you're a consultant you just
want to get more context uh you can use
the link to get to code read that code
if that's something you like to do uh
and get more context or you can use the
new menu item on the field itself that
will take you to the code for the field
specifically so um here we're really
Bridging the Two Worlds between you know
business Central web client and the
runtime with the AL code that runs all
of that behind the
scenes now page inspection is really
ideal for just one-offs being able to
inspect that occasional field when
you're troubleshooting for example um
but sometimes you really want to bring
that data onto the page so you can use
it repeatedly we've got a great feature
for you here as well uh we're excited to
announce that with update 2 three we're
also introducing the ability to add
existing table fields to your pages so
you can optimize them you can adjust
that layout bring the right data in at
the right time these fields are not
editable so you're really just bringing
in Source table fields which are going
to be readon you can only view those
values uh but it's really going to help
you get unblocked uh you know do
something you've never been able to do
before bring that field from The Source
table drag it onto the page whether it's
a list page or a card page it works on
any page type um and around this we've
enhanced the user experience to really
help you you know understand the
situation with these fields give you
more context and transparency so that
you can really make sure you're getting
the right fields and making changes that
are safe and one last thing we've added
to the UI customization tooling is the
ability to make Fields readon this means
you take any editable field you can now
lock it lock its editability becomes
read only so you've cleaned up the page
you know visually it doesn't distract
you from the editable fields that you
want to be modifying and enter data into
it also prevents you know data entry
accidents as
well so last wave we also introduced
analysis tabs uh this was released in
preview a whole new way of deriving
insights from your data without having
to switch apps without the need for
development in wave two this is now
generally available for all of our
customers uh and based on your feedback
we've improved a whole bunch of things
here as well we've improved the
experience for example you can actually
share
um a link to your newly crafted analysis
tab with your co-workers again as I
mentioned earlier the name of the
analysis tab will actually be included
in that hyperlink you can provide more
control uh over who has access to
analysis mode uh and on which Pages as
well there's no limits to the data
volume that you can actually bring into
these analysis views as well uh and
finally we're also going Beyond lists um
in terms of now applying the same
experience also to queries and query
objects some of these topics really
deserve their own Deep dive session so
if you have a few more minutes I highly
recommend you take a look at these um we
have one session about the analyzing
data on lists we got another one about
UI customization tooling and I also
recommend this third session as well uh
about mobile apps because we know that
productivity goes beyond just the
desktop sometimes you need to take
business Central into your pocket and on
the go and even there doesn't need to be
productive so join that session to hear
about how you can search for pages and
data more effectively but also use new
features like barcode scanning to do so
much
more so there's plenty more resources if
you want to learn more about business
Central uh if you want to follow the
buzz and social media or if you just
want to connect with the product
engineering team people such as myself
uh well we started off by saying that
you know customers may want to type and
click less and I hope you've gotten a a
a good sense of that throughout this
session but if you've got that next
great idea that you think will save our
customers a whole bunch of time we're
listening we're listening to your
feedback you can submit your great ideas
at
aka.ms BC
ideas so it's been a real pleasure to
show you how we're improving the web
client in 2023 release Wave 2 on behalf
of the business Central team thanks for
tuning in and we wish you a productive
workday